<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="manual.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE document-root [
        <!ELEMENT document (title, item+)>
        <!ELEMENT item ((item | (heading, text?))+)>
        <!ELEMENT title (#PCDATA)>
        <!ELEMENT heading (#PCDATA)>
        <!ELEMENT text (#PCDATA)>
        <!ATTLIST heading id ID #REQUIRED>
        ]>
<document>
    <title>JSCover User Manual</title>

    <item>
        <heading id="generalInformation">General Information</heading>
        <text>
            This document is not yet complete...but should be soon.
            For an overview of the basic workings of of JSCover, see the
            <a href="http://siliconforks.com/jscoverage/manual.html" target="_blank">JSCoverage documentation</a>
        </text>
        <item>
            <heading id="introduction">Introduction</heading>
            <text>
                JSCover is a tool that measures code coverage for JavaScript programs.
                It is based on the popular JSCoverage, with the C++/SpiderMonkey instrumentation replaced with
                Java/Rhino.
            </text>
            <text>
                JSCover works by adding instrumentation to JavaScript code before it is executed in a web browser.
                JSCover provides several alternative ways of doing this:
                <ul>
                    <li>The simplest method is to use the file-system mode program to generate instrumented JavaScript
                        files.
                    </li>
                    <li>Alternatively, you can use the server mode, a simple web server that instruments JavaScript code
                        as
                        it is served.
                    </li>
                    <li>Finally, server mode can be run with the --proxy option to act as a proxy server which
                        instruments
                        any JavaScript code proxied through it.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </text>
            <text>
                The server mode has two advantages:
                <ol>
                    <li>can store coverage reports to the filesystem (with/without the proxy option)</li>
                    <li>can include unloaded/untested JavaScript (only without the proxy option)</li>
                </ol>
            </text>
        </item>
        <item>
            <heading id="packaging">Packaging</heading>
            <text>
                JSCover comes packaged in two JARs.
                The first option is preferred to avoid class-path issues, especially as JSCover may be using a
                non-standard
                version on Rhino (e.g. built from trunk).
            </text>
            <text>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        JSCover-all.jar
                        which includes all dependencies
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        JSCover.jar
                        which must have all dependent JARs available in the same directory
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </text>
            <text>
                A log file is also produced in the output directory which should be inspected after running.
                It will contain any errors that occurred during instrumentation.
            </text>
        </item>
    </item>
    <item>
        <heading id="usage">Usage</heading>
        <item>
            <heading id="usage">General</heading>
            <text>
                <code>java -jar JSCover-all.jar [OPTIONS]...</code>
                <code>java -jar JSCover.jar [OPTIONS]...</code>
            </text>
            <text>
                Command line options are:
            </text>
            <text>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Option</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>-ws</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>Run in&#160;<b>w</b>eb&#160;<b>s</b>erver mode - see
                            <a href="#serverMode">below</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>-fs</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>Run in&#160;<b>f</b>ile&#160;<b>s</b>ystem mode - see
                            <a href="#fileMode">below</a>
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>-h,--help</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>Display command line help</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>-V,--version</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>Display version</td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </text>
        </item>
        <item>
            <heading id="serverMode">Server Mode</heading>
            <text>
                <code>java -jar JSCover-all.jar -ws [OPTIONS]</code>
                For example:
                <code>java -jar JSCover-all.jar -ws --port=80 --no-instrument=lib --no-instrument=test</code>
            </text>
            <text>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Option</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>-h,--help</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>Display command line help</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--document-root=PATH</td>
                        <td>current directory</td>
                        <td>Serve web content from the directory given by PATH (can be relative or absolute)</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--no-instrument=URL</td>
                        <td>None</td>
                        <td>Specify URLs not to be instrumented. Can be specified multiple times.</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--report-dir=PATH</td>
                        <td>current directory</td>
                        <td>Use the directory given by PATH (can be relative or absolute) for storing coverage
                            reports.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--port=PORT</td>
                        <td>8080</td>
                        <td>Specify the port to listen on</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--proxy</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>Run in proxy mode</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--include-unloaded-js</td>
                        <td>false</td>
                        <td>
                            When storing report in web-server mode, search beneath the document root path for JavaScript
                            file not served and include in the coverage report. Not compatible with --proxy. Will
                            respect --no-instrument.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--js-version=VERSION</td>
                        <td>1.5</td>
                        <td>
                            Use the specified JavaScript version; valid values for VERSION are
                            <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JavaScript#Versions" target="_blank">1.0, 1.1, 1.2,
                                ..., 1.8</a>.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </text>
            <item>
                <heading id="implementationStoreReport">Storing reports</heading>
                <text>
                    The store button triggers the POSTing of the coverage data to the server in JSON format. The
                    following will then occur:
                    <ul>
                        <li>If a JSON file, jscoverage.json, already exists, the coverage data will be merged</li>
                        <li>
                            If no JSON file exists, but --include-unloaded-js is present, all un-loaded JavaScript
                            files will be merged with the submitted JSON and saved to the report
                        </li>
                        <li>If neither of the above is true, the raw JSON is stored</li>
                    </ul>
                </text>
            </item>
            <item>
                <heading id="jsReportStorage">Programmatic Report Storage</heading>
                <text>
                    If you are executing a test suite using the server-mode, you can store a coverage report
                    programmatically by having your test suite call the jscoverage_report function (automatically
                    generated by JSCover) after all your tests have finished running:

<code>if (window.jscoverage_report) {
  jscoverage_report();
}</code>

                    You can specify the name of the directory in which to store the report by passing the name as a
                    parameter to the jscoverage_report function:

<code>if (window.jscoverage_report) {
  // determine the directory name based on the browser
  var directory;
  if (/MSIE/.test(navigator.userAgent)) {
    directory = 'IE';
  }
  else {
    directory = 'other';
  }
  jscoverage_report(directory);
}</code>

                    This directory will be a subdirectory under the jscoverage-report/ directory (or whatever is
                    specified with the --report-dir option). Using the above example, the report would be stored to
                    either jscoverage-report/IE/ or jscoverage-report/other/.
                </text>
                <text>
                    It is not necessary that your test suite be executed within the jscoverage.html web interface to
                    store a coverage report. The URL of the test suite can simply be loaded directly in a web browser.
                </text>
                <text>
                    The example in doc/example-jsunit/ demonstrates storing coverage reports programmatically.
                </text>
            </item>
        </item>
        <item>
            <heading id="fileMode">File Mode</heading>
            <text>
                <code>java -jar JSCover-all.jar -fs [OPTIONS] SOURCE-DIRECTORY DESTINATION-DIRECTORY</code>
                For example:
                <code>java -jar JSCover-all.jar -fs --no-instrument=lib --no-instrument=test</code>
            </text>
            <text>
                <table>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Option</th>
                        <th>Default</th>
                        <th>Description</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>-h,--help</td>
                        <td>N/A</td>
                        <td>Display command line help</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--no-instrument=URL</td>
                        <td>None</td>
                        <td>Specify URLs not to be instrumented. Can be specified multiple times.</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--exclude=PATH</td>
                        <td>None</td>
                        <td>Copies SOURCE-DIRECTORY to DESTINATION-DIRECTORY recursively, but does not copy
                            SOURCE-DIRECTORY/PATH. PATH must be a complete path relative to SOURCE-DIRECTORY. PATH can
                            be a file or a directory (in which case the directory and its entire contents are skipped).
                            This option may be given multiple times.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>--js-version=VERSION</td>
                        <td>1.5</td>
                        <td>
                            Use the specified JavaScript version; valid values for VERSION are
                            <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JavaScript#Versions" target="_blank">1.0, 1.1, 1.2,
                                ..., 1.8</a>.
                        </td>
                    </tr>
                </table>
            </text>
            <text>
                The first step is to add instrumentation to your JavaScript code. You do this by executing jscoverage
                with two arguments:
                <code>java -jar JSCover-all.jar -fs SOURCE-DIRECTORY DESTINATION-DIRECTORY</code>
            </text>
            <text>
                SOURCE-DIRECTORY is the directory containing the JavaScript code to be instrumented, and
                DESTINATION-DIRECTORY is the name of the directory to which JSCover should output the instrumented
                code. The JSCover program will create DESTINATION-DIRECTORY if necessary and (recursively) copy
                SOURCE-DIRECTORY to DESTINATION-DIRECTORY, instrumenting any files ending with a .js extension.
            </text>
            <text>
                The directory structure under SOURCE-DIRECTORY will be preserved, so that if you have a file
                SOURCE-DIRECTORY/dir/index.html referencing the script SOURCE-DIRECTORY/dir/script.js, then JSCover
                will create a copy of the HTML file at DESTINATION-DIRECTORY/dir/index.html and an instrumented version
                of the script at DESTINATION-DIRECTORY/dir/script.js. In addition, JSCover will create a file called
                jscoverage.html which will be used to execute the instrumented code.
                <code>java -jar JSCover-all.jar -fs SOURCE-DIRECTORY DESTINATION-DIRECTORY</code>
            </text>
            <text>
                <table class="noBorder">
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <code>
<var>SOURCE-DIRECTORY</var>/
    dir/
        index.html
        script.js
                                </code>
                            </td>
                            <td class="arrow">&#8594;</td>
                            <td>
                                <code>
<var>DESTINATION-DIRECTORY</var>/
    dir/
        index.html
        script.js [instrumented]
        jscoverage.html
                                </code>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </text>
            <text>
                For the example code in the doc/example/ directory, you can execute the following command line from the
                top-level directory of the JSCoverage distribution:
                <code>java -jar JSCover-all.jar -fs doc/example doc/instrumented</code>
            </text>
            <text>
                This will create the directory doc/instrumented/ and place an instrumented copy of the code from
                doc/example/ in doc/instrumented/.
            </text>
            <text>
                <table class="noBorder">
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td>
                                <code>
doc/example/
    index.html
    script.js
                                </code>
                            </td>
                            <td class="arrow">&#8594;</td>
                            <td>
                                <code>
doc/instrumented/
    index.html
    script.js [instrumented]
    jscoverage.html
                                </code>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </text>
        </item>
    </item>
    <item>
        <heading id="execModes">Execution Modes</heading>
        <item>
            <heading id="iframeMode">IFrame Mode</heading>
            <text>
                <img src="images/screenshot.png"/>
            </text>
        </item>
        <item>
            <heading id="windowMode">Window Mode</heading>
            <text>
                In some situations it may be difficult to execute your code within the
                &lt;iframe&gt;
                in the JSCover "Browser" tab. For example, the code may assume that it is running in the top-level
                browser window, generating errors if it is executed from within a frame. JSCover has an alternative
                mode of operation, called window mode, which may be useful in this case.
            </text>
            <text>
                To use JSCover in window mode, load your URL by clicking the "Open in window" button instead of the
                "Open in frame" button. This will cause your URL to be opened in a new window. (Depending on your
                browser settings, it may be opened in a new browser tab instead.) Execute your code in this new window,
                and then return to the jscoverage.html window and click the "Summary" tab to get code coverage
                statistics.
            </text>
        </item>
        <item>
            <heading id="invertedMode">Inverted Mode</heading>
            <text>
                There is another alternative mode of operation, called inverted mode. Like window mode, this allows you
                to avoid running your code inside an &lt;iframe&gt;.
            </text>
            <text>
                Normally you load jscoverage.html in your web browser, and in its "Browser" tab you launch your test
                code.
                In inverted mode, you do the opposite: you load your test page directly in your web browser, and from
                there you launch JSCover.
                To do this you need to add some code to your test page:
                <code>window.open('path/to/jscoverage.html');</code>
            </text>
            <text>
                The "path/to/jscoverage.html" should be a URL pointing to the location of the jscoverage.html file
                (remember, this will be in the top level of the DESTINATION-DIRECTORY you specified when running the
                jscoverage executable).
            </text>
            <text>
                You can place this code wherever you like in your page: for example, you could attach it to a button:
                <code>&lt;button type="button" onclick="window.open('path/to/jscoverage.html');"&gt;Coverage report&lt;/button&gt;</code>
            </text>
            <text>Note that you must use a window.open call; simply making a link to jscoverage.html is not
                sufficient.
            </text>
            <text>An example is located in the doc/example-inverted directory. You can instrument the code with the
                jscoverage program:
            </text>
            <text><code>jscoverage doc/example-inverted doc/instrumented-inverted</code></text>
            <text>You can load the page doc/instrumented-inverted/index.html directly in your web browser. From this
                page, you select one of the radio buttons and then click the "Coverage report" button to launch the
                JSCover report.
            </text>
            <text>Another example is located in the doc/example-jsunit directory. See the FAQ for more information.
            </text>
        </item>
        <item>
            <heading id="queryStringOptions">Query String Options</heading>
            <text>
                When accessing jscoverage.html in a web browser, you may provide a query string consisting of options
                separated by ampersand (&amp;) or semicolon (;). Any option not containing an equals sign (=) is
                considered to be a URL which will be loaded in the &lt;iframe&gt; within the "Browser" tab.
            </text>
            <text>
                u=URL, url=URL, frame=URL, f=URL<br/>
                Load URL in the &lt;iframe&gt;
                within the "Browser" tab. (This is the same as specifying an option without an equals sign.)
            </text>
            <text>
                w=URL, window=URL<br/>
                Load URL in a new window (window mode).
            </text>
            <text>
                m=BOOLEAN, missing=BOOLEAN<br/>
                Determines whether to initially display the "Missing" column in the "Summary" tab. BOOLEAN can be true,
                t, yes, y, on, 1 (to display the "Missing" column), or false, f, no, n, off, 0 (to hide the "Missing"
                column). By default, the "Missing" column is not displayed.
            </text>
        </item>
    </item>
    <item>
        <heading id="other">Other</heading>
        <item>
            <heading id="jsCoverageVJSCover">JSCover V. JSCoverage</heading>
            <item>
                <heading id="jsCoverageVJSCoverImplementation">Implementation</heading>
                <text>
                    The main difference in the implementation is the tools used for parsing.
                    All JavaScript code is the same, and so the UI interaction is the same.
                </text>
                <text>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Tool</th>
                            <th>Parser Language</th>
                            <th>Parser Implementation</th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>JSCover</td>
                            <td>Java</td>
                            <td>
                                <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/rhino/">Rhino</a>
                                1.7R5pre
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td>JSCoverage</td>
                            <td>C/C++</td>
                            <td>
                                <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/SpiderMonkey">SpiderMonkey</a>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </text>
                <text>
                    As SpiderMonkey is used in FireFox which is used for much development and testing of web-based
                    JavaScript, it is arguably the best JavaScript implementation currently available.
                </text>
            </item>
        </item>
    </item>
    <item>
        <heading id="howWork">How does it work</heading>
        <item>
            <heading id="implementationInstrumentation">Instrumentation</heading>
            <text>
                JSCover works by instrumenting the specified JavaScript. A simple example is shown below:
                <code>alert('Hello World!');</code>
                ...becomes...
                <code>
//...header code above
if (! this._$jscoverage) {
this._$jscoverage = {};
}
if (! _$jscoverage['test.js']) {
_$jscoverage['test.js'] = [];
_$jscoverage['test.js'][1] = 0;
}
_$jscoverage['test.js'].source = ["alert('Hello World!');"];
_$jscoverage['test.js'][1]++;
alert('Hello World!');
                </code>
                This illustrates that when the target code is executed, a counter for the file name and line
                is incremented. The header code manages the declaration of _$jscoverage.
            </text>
        </item>
    </item>
</document>
